Elif Akata

♥ Munich, Germany ☎ Google Scholar ♥ eliaka ☻ @elifakata և elifakata ♦ https://eliaka.github.io/

I'm a PhD student working at the intersection of cognitive science and machine learning. My research focuses on understanding how LLMs behave as social, collaborative agents and how we can design systems that effectively interact, adapt, and communicate in dynamic environments.

EDUCATION

University of Tübingen Ph.D. Machine Learning & Cognitive Science International Max Planck Research School for Intelligent Systems (IMPRS-IS)	since Oct 2022 Tübingen & Munich, Germany
University of Tübingen M.Sc. Computer Science Thesis on automated attention detection in classroom videos (HCl Lab)	Oct 2019 – Feb 2022 Tübingen, Germany
Saarland University B.Sc. Computer Science Thesis on EMG-based hand gesture recognition system (HCl Lab)	Oct 2015 – Sep 2019 Saarbrücken, Germany

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Helmholtz Munich & University of Tübingen | Ph.D. Researcher

Oct 2022 - Present

Human-Centered AI Lab, supervised by Dr. Eric Schulz and Prof. Dr. Matthias Bethge

Tübingen Al Center | Resesarch Assistant

Oct 2021 - Sep 2022

In the Computational Neuroscience and Machine Learning lab of Prof. Dr. Matthias Bethge, worked on computational creativity and generative art

University of Tübingen | Resesarch Assistant

Aug 2021 - Sep 2021

In the Human Computer Interaction lab of Prof. Dr. Enkelejda Kasneci, prepared and analysed data for an attention-based automated classroom activity detection system

Max Planck Institute for Intelligent Systems | Research Assistant

Sep 2020 - Nov 2020

In the Haptic Intelligence department of Dr. Katherine Kuchenbecker, worked on the sensor-specific part of an ASL sign-recognition device

Max Planck Institute for Software Systems | Student Research Assistant

London School of Economics | Generative AI in Social Science Research Workshop

May 2017 - Apr 2019

2024

In the Programming Analysis and Verification group of Dr. Eva Darulova, wrote benchmark programs for the Daisy numerical optimization framework and performed evaluations on Arduinos

TEACHING & SUMMER SCHOOLS

MIT Brains, Minds & Machines Summer Course Woods Hole, USA	2024
International Computer Vision Summer School (ICVSS) Sicily, Italy	2023
Trustworthy Machine Learning TA for a 6 Credit M.Sc. lecture at University of Tübingen	2023
INVITED TALKS	
University College London Experimental Psychology Department	2024

SKILLS

Languages: English (IELTS Academic Band 7.5), German (DSH-2, CEFR Level C1), Turkish (Native)

Coding: Python, C/C++, PyTorch, Numpy, Pandas, SciKit-Learn, Git, LLM fine-tuning (SFT, GRPO) on HPC